# José Jair Santanna

Enthusiastic, Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

## Contact

Mooienhof 10, 45 7512EB Enschede, The Netherlands. +31 (6) 42330703 j.j.santanna@utwente.nl

## **Programming**

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark/Scala & Impala

## Links

http://jairsantanna.com



jjcsantanna **f** 

jjcsantanna **W** 

# Languages Portuguese $\star$ $\star$ $\star$ $\star$ English $\star$ $\star$ $\star$ Spanish $\star$ $\star$ $\Leftrightarrow$ $\Leftrightarrow$

Dutch★☆☆☆☆

## **Professional Objective**

I am currently a PhD candidate at University of Twente (till march 2017) in a research group called Design and Analysis of Communication Systems (DACS). My research is founded by the European commission via a project focus in network of excellence, called Flamingo; and by the Dutch national Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) in a project called Distributed Denial of Service Defence (D3).

I am interested in a research & development position with focus on network management and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis and network operations. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation to improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

## **Education**

2013-mar/2017\*Doctor in Computer Science

University of Twente, The Netherlands

"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon". Supervisor: Prof. dr. ir. Aiko Pras

2010–2012 **Master** in Computer Science

Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil

"A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain Circuit Management". The outcome of this work generated a product still in use by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/).

Supervisor: Prof. dr. Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville

2005–2010 **Bachelor** in Computer Engineer

Federal University of Pará, Brazil

"A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Protocol in Mesh Networks."

Supervisor: Dr. Kelvin Lopes Dias

## **Experience**

## **Assistant Professor**

2012–2013 University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Santa Cruz do Sul. Brazil

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and **teach** the following courses: Digital Systems, Computer Networks, and Computer Network Management. The lectures included topics such as the core networking protocols (e.g., TCP/IP, BGP and DNS) and ISP management operations, tools and issues.

## **Technical Adviser**

2016 To the Yokohama National University

Japan

For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the *Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications*.

2016 To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

tation Center

The Netherlands

For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware" requested by the *Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice*.

## **Guest Lecturer**

2016 **Network Management** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Title: SNMPv1, v2, v3 and Beyond (a very practical lecture)

Link: https://github.com/jjsantanna/lectures\_hands\_on/tree/

master/20160517\_SNMPv1\_v2\_v3

Audience: master students of computer science, electrical engineer, and

telematics from the University of Twente.

2015 & 2016 **Product Design to Online Business** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students of industrial engineering and business information

technology.

2015 **Network Security** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: master and bachelor students of computer science, electrical engineer, and telematics from the University of Twente, 3TU cyber security, and

members of ICT labs.

2015 Cybercrime & Cybersecurity University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

## **Student Supervisor**

Among 10 supervised students: 5 decided to follow towards the next academic degree[\*], PhD or MSc, 2 received the MSc degree cum laude[+], 2 won the best paper award in international conferences[#], and 1 won the second place of a renowned Dutch national prize (KIVI/Defensie & Veiligheid) for her thesis[!].

[M.Sc. Degree] Justyna Chromik [\*  $^+$   $^\#$  !] , Wouter de Vries [\*  $^\#$ ], Joey de Vries [+], Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak[\*], Max Kerkers[\*], Dirk Maan[\*], Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

## International Conference Reviewer

Among more than 20 venues acting as reviewer we highlight four conferences which are the top well ranked related to the Committee on Network Operation and Management (CNOM), which is a renowned technical committee part of the IEEE Communications Society. For each conference we present the acronym, the full name, the acceptance rate which is the number of papers submitted divided by published\* (according www.cs.ucsb.edu/~almeroth), and the h-index\* (according Google scholar). For the entire list of conference that I was reviewer you can check my records on the known conference management systems, i.e., EDAS [link], JEMS [link], and EasyChair [link].

CNSM	International Conference on Network and Service Management	17.6%   18
NETWORKINGIFIP Networking		
IM	IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management	27.2%   18
NOMS	IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium	28.9%   22

\*last checked: April 7,2016

## **Conference Organizer**

2016	Shadow Technical Program Committee (TPC)	CNSM
------	--	------

IFIP/IEEE International Conference on Network and Service Management (CNSM) is the premier annual single-track conference in the general area of network and service management. A shadow TPC is a experimental initiative to make PhD researchers better TPCs in the future. The reviews are considered

as normal a TPC review.

2013-2016 **Technical Program Committee (TPC)** 

ERRC

Escola Regional de Redes de Computadores, a conference for undergrad stu-

dents from the south of Brazil.

2012 Local Organizing Committee

LatinCloud

IEEE Latin American Conference on Cloud Computing and Communications

2010 Local Organizing Committee

SBRC

The Brazilian Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems.

## **Software Developer**

## 2015–Now Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)

Link: http://www.ddosdb.net

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

## 2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP).

Language: WS-BPEL

#### 2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application part of a Ph.D. thesis [link] sponsored by a subsidiary

(Eletronorte) of the major Brazilian power utility (Eletrobrás).

Language: C#.Net & mySQL

## **Presentations**

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (available on my slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

Invited presentation at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).

Invited Presentation to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).

Invited Presentation to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).

Presentation at the 31<sup>th</sup> and 36<sup>th</sup> IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

## **Awards**

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch' (1 $^{st}$ Plac	e) CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 $^{rd}$ Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award Autonomo	ous Infrastructure, Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Brazilian Sym	posium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 $^{rd}$ Place)	Computer Engineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

CV last update: June 17, 2016

## **Scientific Appendix**

## **Publications**

## DDoS 3.0 - How Terrorists Bring Down the Internet

Aiko Pras, José Jair Santanna, Jessica Steinberger, Anna Sperotto International GI/ITG Conference, MMB & DFT, 2016

## "Ludo" - kids playing Distributed Denial of Service

Jessica Steinberger, José Jair Santanna, Evangelos Spatharas, Hendrik Amler, Niklas Breuer, Kristian Graul, Benjamin Kuhnert, Ulrike Piontek, Anna Sperotto, Harald Baier, Aiko Pras TERENA Networking Conference (TNC), 2016

#### Booter websites characterization: Towards a list of threats

Justyna Joanna Chromik, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras Brazilian Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems (SBRC), 2015

#### Inside Booters: An Analysis on Operational Databases

José Jair Santanna, Romain Durban, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

## Booters - An Analysis of DDoS-as-a-Service Attacks.

José Jair Santanna, Roland Rijswijk-Deij, Anna Sperotto, Rick Hofstede, Mark Wierbosch, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Aiko Pras

IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

## How Asymmetric Is the Internet? A Study to Support the Use of Traceroute

Wouter Vries, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2015

#### Characterisation of the Kelihos.B Botnet

Max Kerkers, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

## Towards Validation of the Internet Census 2012

Dirk Maan, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Pieter-Tjerk Boer EUNICE/IFIP International Workshop (EUNICE), 2014

#### Characterizing and Mitigating The DDoS-as-a-Service Phenomenon

José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

## Through the Internet of Things - A Management by Delegation Smart Object Aware System (MbDSAS)

Marcelo Marotta, Felipe Carbone, José Jair Santanna, Liane Tarouco *IEEE Computer Software and Applications Conference (COMPSAC)*, 2013

## Redes de Rádios Cognitivos: Arquiteturas, Sensoriamento Espectral e Questões Regulatórias.

Rafael Kunst, Cristiano Both, Lucas Bondan, Maicon Kist, José Jair Santanna, Leonardo Faganello, Lisandro Granville, Juergen Rochol

Simpósio Brasileiro de Telecomunicações (SBrT). 2012

#### A BPM-based solution for inter-domain circuit management

José Jair Santanna, Juliano Wickboldt, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS), 2012

#### Internet of Things in healthcare: Interoperatibility and security issues

Liane Tarouco, Leandro Bertholdo, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Lucas Arbiza, Marcelo Marotta, José Jair Santanna

IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC), 2012